(2 Corinthians 12:2): St Paul declares, ‘I know a man who fourteen years ago was caught up into the third heaven; whether in the body or no I cannot tell: God knoweth.
Now granting Paul was there at any time, then either body and soul both turned to spirit or else his soul took wing out of his body.
It is certain that his soul left not his body, for she was giving life unto his body; she must then have seen God in her and herself in him.
The soul has three powers: mind, will and rage.
These three powers are in league with deity.
Will cleaving unto God can do all things.
God seized of his divinity bestows upon her power and fecundity.
Mind cleaving to the Son knows with the Son; it knows with the Son when it is void of knowledge.
The third power is the power of attack, which is connected with the Holy Ghost.
This power is ever making for the source whence it proceeded forth and the Holy Ghost is its initiator into the eternal nature: it floods the secret chamber of the soul, and lo!
she loses time and place in the eternal, in time transcending time.
But for the soul this is not enough: had she enough she would have time in lieu of her eternity.
Let us not flag.
Not ours the blame if, being ready and atoned in will, God hides himself so that we cannot do all things with him although he plays his part just as the sun gives out its light and fire gives out its heat.
Woodapples cannot check the letting of their gall, but God contrives from time to time to reach out to the longing soul if he is very near to her.
So let her, never doubting, with hearty longing, hail God frequently: ‘O Friend of me, how long am I to wait for thee?
He says, to Christ was given a new name: one by the angel, another by St Paul, a third by his heavenly Father.
The angel gave him the name Jesus Christ.
Joseph and Mary called him by this name which signifies Weal of the World.
The name is given to the wounded soul.
Alas, we are too frail!
We should be well of our infirmities being raised up and gotten in; we should be raised if we were destitute and unattached.
For the exalted spark wherein we see the light divine, that never parts from God nor is there anything between.
What matter then if good and ill and pain betide, they do but touch the lower faculties.
St Paul gave him three names and called him the reflection of the Father.
He says, the wounded soul is given the mystic heavenly bread.
Whence comes her wound?—From longing.
What is longing?—It is love.
What is nobler than longing?
What we pray God for humbly and with longing he durst not refuse: desire ablush with modesty he leads into the triple chamber of the Holy Trinity.
Paul called him also the fecundity of the Father and the image in the Father, working with the Father to bring forth his Person.
Verily I say, the soul will bring forth Person if God laughs into her and she laughs back to him.
To speak in parable, the Father laughs into the Son and the Son laughs back to the Father; and this laughter breeds liking, and liking breeds joy, and joy begets love, and love begets Person, and Person begets the Holy Ghost.
In this wise does he travail with his Father.
The third name he gave was, The Majesty of the Substance of God.
Majesty is the essence of his divine substance, this substance being the elemental matter of the three Persons.
The soul is called majesty when she gives up mode: then she knows the Father and paternity, the Son and filiation, and the Persons of them twain she comprehends in unity.
The Father gave him five names, ineffable.
God keep us every whit in him.
So help us God.
Amen.