To return to the subject of the eternal birth.
There is the question whether the soul brings forth the eternal Word in images or imageless?
Remember this.
When the soul resigns herself to God and is atoned with him and God undertakes her work, she is receptive merely and leaves God to act.
Here the soul is pregnant without form or image, for anything conceived in form or image trenches upon time and place and is akin to creatures; whence it follows that the more the work is of the soul the less it is of God.
The soul conceives more truly without images than in them, for this birth is more by way of Godhood than of selfhood.
But we may still enquire, in which image does the soul best succeed in giving birth to the eternal Word?
There are three kinds of images.
The first the soul takes in from without through the senses.
The second the soul conjures up from within by thinking on the childhood of our Lord or on his martyrdom; but all images so gotten are called divine births in the soul.
The third kind of images is given to the soul by God direct.
It is in these last that the soul conceives the best.
According to another gloss: this happens when the mind engenders, feels and knows the eternal Word in its proper image as gotten by the Father in himself, supposing the soul able to attain thereto; or, intellect failing her for this, when, faring forth in faith and love, he reaches out to this same image: for in this final image the eternal Word is born most perfectly of all.
Another question is, whether the birth of the eternal Word is fleeting or essential?
Now you must understand that it is this birth which unifies the soul, and in this respect it is intrinsic and passes not away unless a man should fall into mortal sin.
But as happening in the sensible perceptions and in the discursive mind this birth is fugitive.
Further, it is asked, in what particular place does the soul bring forth or seek the eternal Word?
Mark.
It is in the Father as the intellectual image of his divine essence and is the reflection of his divine nature, so that it embodies both his essence and his nature.
It is with the Father as the filial Person.
It is in the Holy Ghost as the exuberance of their eternal satisfaction.
It is in the soul as the likeness of God’s equal forms (or Persons).
It is in all creatures as the preserver of their being.
It is here the soul must seek the eternal Word, here in these places, and Christ says: ‘Seek and ye shall find.
May we so seek as to find eternally.
So help us almighty God.
I will say no more at this collation.
Pray God to fit me for this blessed moment.
Amen.