Where is he who is born King of the Jews?
Now concerning this birth, mark where it befalls.
I say again as I have often said before that this birth befalls in the soul exactly as it does in eternity, neither more nor less, for it is the same birth: this birth befalls in the ground and essence of the soul.
Certain questions arise.
Granting that God is in all things as intelligence (or mind) and is more instinct in things than they are in themselves and more natural; and granting that God wherever he is is in operation, knowing himself and speaking his Word, then mark in what respects the soul is better fitted for this divine operation than other rational creatures God exists in.
God is in all things as being, as activity, as power.
But he is procreative in the soul alone for though every creature is a vestige of God, the soul is the natural image of God.
This image is perfected and adorned in this birth.
No creature but the soul is susceptible to this birth, this act.
Such perfection as enters the soul, whether it be divine light, grace or bliss, must needs enter the soul in this birth and no otherwise.
Do but foster this birth in thee and thou shalt experience all good and all comfort, all happiness, all being and all truth.
What comes to thee therein brings thee true being and stability and whatsoever thou mayst seek or grasp, without it, perishes, take it how thou wilt.
This alone gives life; all else corrupts.
Moreover, in this birth thou dost participate in the divine influx and its gifts.
This is not received by creatures wherein God’s image is not found: the soul-idea belongs to the eternal birth alone and this happens only and solely in the soul, begotten of the Father in the ground and innermost recesses of the soul whereinto never image shone nor soul-power peeped.
Another question is: If this birth befalls in the ground and essence of the soul, then it happens alike in sinner and in saint, so what use or good is it to me?
The ground of nature is the same in both, nay even in hell the nobility of nature persists eternally.—It is characteristic of this birth that it always comes with fresh light.
It always brings great enlightenment to the soul because it is the nature of good to diffuse itself.
In this birth God pours into the soul in such abundance of light, the ground and essence of the soul are so flooded with it, that it runs over into her powers and into the outward man as well.
Thus it befell Paul when upon his journey God touched him with his light and spake to him: the reflection of this light showed outwardly so that his companions saw it surrounding Paul like the saints.
The superfluity of light in the ground of the soul wells over into the body which is filled with radiance.
No sinner can receive this light nor is he worthy to, being full of sin and wickedness, or darkness.
As he (John) says, ‘The darkness neither receives nor comprehends the light.
Because the avenues by which the light would enter are choked and obstructed with guile and darkness.
Light and darkness are incompatible, like God and creatures.
Enter God, exit creatures.
Man is quite conscious of this light.
Directly he turns to God this light begins to glint and sparkle in him, telling him what to do and what to leave undone, with many a shrewd hint to boot of things he hitherto ignored and knew nothing of.—How dost thou know?—Suppose thy heart is vehemently moved to retire from the world.
How could that be if not by this light?
It is so charming, so delightful, it makes other things so tiresome which are not God or God’s.
It attracts thee to God and thou art sensible of many a virtuous impulse albeit uncertain whence it comes.
This interior mood is in no wise due to creatures nor is it any of their bidding, for what creatures effect and direct comes in from without.
But thy ground alone is stirred by this force and the freer thou dost keep the more truth and discernment are thine.
No man was ever lost save for the reason that once having left his ground he has let himself become too permanently settled abroad.
St Augustine says: Many there be that have sought light and truth but only abroad where they are not.
They finally go out so far that they never get back nor find their way in again.
Neither have these found the truth for the truth is within in their ground, not without.
So he who means to see this light and find out the whole truth must foster the awareness of this birth within himself, in his ground, so shall his powers all be lighted up and his outer man as well.
Directly God inwardly stirs his ground with the truth its light darts into his powers, and lo, that man knows more than anyone could teach him.
As the prophet says, ‘I know more than I was ever taught.
It is because this light cannot lighten and shine in sinners that this birth cannot occur in them.
This birth is inconsistent with darkness and sin therefore it befalls not in the powers but in the ground and essence of the soul.
Then comes the question: If God the Father labours only in the ground and essence of the soul, not in her powers, what have the powers got to do with it?
How do they help by being idle and taking holiday?
What is the use, seeing this birth befalls not in the powers?—It is well asked.
But consider.
Every creature works towards some end.
The end is ever the first in intention and the last in execution.
And God too works for a wholly blessed end, to wit, himself: to bring the soul and all her powers into that end, into himself.
For this God’s works are wrought, for this the Father brings his Son to birth in the soul, that all the powers of the soul may end in this.
He lies in wait for all the soul contains, all are bidden to his royal feast.
Here, the soul is scattered abroad among her powers and dissipated in the act of each: the power of seeing in the eye, the power of hearing in the ear, the power of tasting in the tongue, and her powers are accordingly enfeebled for their interior work, scattered forces being imperfect.
It follows that for her interior work to be effective, she must call in all her powers, recollecting them out of extended things to one interior act.
St Augustine says, ‘The soul is where she loves rather than where she animates the body.
Once upon a time there was a heathen philosopher who studied mathematics.
He was sitting by the embers making calculations in pursuance of his art when there came along a man brandishing a sword, who, not witting that it was the master, cried out, ‘Quick, thy name, or I shall slay thee!
The master was too much absorbed to see or hear his enemy and failed to catch the threat.
So after hailing him several times the enemy cut off his head.
And this to acquire a mere natural science!
How much more does it behove us to withdraw from things in order to concentrate our powers on perceiving and knowing the one infinite and immortal truth!
To this end do thou assemble thy entire mind and memory: turn them into the ground where thy treasure lies hid.
But for this thou must drop all other activities; thou must get to unknowing to find it.
The question is, Were it not better for each power to go on with its own work, then none would hinder the others in their work nor yet God in his?
Can there not be creaturely knowledge in me that is no hindrance, as God knows all things without hindrance and so do the saints?—I answer: The saints behold God in a simple image and in that image they discern all things; and God himself sees himself thus, perceiving all things in himself.
He need not turn, as we do, from one thing to another.
Supposing that in this life we were always confronted with a mirror wherein we see and recognise all things at a glance in one single image: neither act nor knowledge would be a hindrance then.
At present we must turn from one thing to another: we can only mind one thing at the expense of all the others.
And the soul is bound so straitly to her powers that where they flow she must flow with them; the soul must be present at everything they do, and attentive too, or nothing would come of their exertions.
The drain of attending to external acts is bound to weaken her interior operation.
For this nativity God wants, and he must have, a vacant, free and unencumbered soul wherein is nothing but himself alone, which waits for naught and nobody but him.
As Christ says: ‘Whoso loveth aught but me, whoso cleaveth to father or mother, or many other things, he is not worthy of me.
I came not upon earth to bring peace but a sword: to cut away all things, to part thee from brother, child, mother and friend, which are really thy foes.
For verily thy comforts are thy foes.
Doth thine eye see all things and thine ear hear all things and thy heart remember them all, then in these things thy soul is destroyed.
A master says, ‘To achieve the interior act one must assemble all one’s powers as it were into one corner of one’s soul, where, secreted from images and forms one is able to work.
We must sink into oblivion and ignorance.
In this silence, this quiet, the Word is heard.
There is no better method of approaching this Word than in silence, in quiet: we hear it and know it aright in unknowing.
To one who knows naught it is clearly revealed.
Haply thou wilt object: ‘You place our salvation in ignorance, Sir.
That seems a mistake.
God made man to know: “Lord make them to know,” says the prophet.
Where there is ignorance there is defect and illusion: he is a brutish man, an ape, a fool, and so remains as long as he is ignorant.
But this is transformed knowledge, not ignorance which comes from lack of knowing; it is by knowing that we get to this unknowing.
Then we know with divine knowing, then our ignorance is ennobled and adorned with supernatural knowledge.
Then in our passion we are more perfect than in action.
According to one authority, the sense of hearing is much nobler than the sense of sight, for we learn wisdom more by ear than eye and live this life more wisely.
We read about a heathen philosopher who was lying at death’s door while his pupils were discussing in his presence some noble science, that, lifting up his dying head and listening, he exclaimed, ‘O teach me even now this art that I may practise it eternally!
Hearing draws in more, seeing leads out more, the very act of seeing.
In eternal life we are far more happy in our ability to hear than in our power to see, because the act of hearing the eternal Word is in me, whereas the act of seeing goes forth from me: hearing, I am receptive; seeing, I am active.
But our bliss does not consist in being active but in being receptive to God.
As God excels creature, so is God’s work more excellent than mine.
It was out of love that God did set our happiness in suffering, for we undergo far more than we do and receive incomparably more than in return we give; moreover, each divine gift is the preparation for some new and richer gift, each gift increasing our capacity and our desire to receive a greater still.
Some theologians say that the soul is symmetrical with God in this respect.
For as God is infinite in giving, so the soul is infinite in receiving or conceiving.
And the soul is as profound to suffer as God is omnipotent to act, hence her transformation by God into God.
God must act and the soul must suffer; for him to know and love himself in her, for her to know with his knowledge, love with his love; and since she is far happier in his than hers it follows that her happiness depends upon his work more than on her own.
The pupils of St Dionysius asked him why Timothy outstripped them in perfection?
Dionysius said, ‘Timothy is a God-receptive man.
He who is expert at this outstrippeth all men.
In this sense thy unknowing is not a defect but thy chief perfection, and suffering thy highest activity.
Kill thy activities and still thy faculties if thou wouldst realise this birth in thee.
To find the newborn King in thee all else thou mightest find must be passed by and left behind thee.
May we outstrip and leave behind such things as are not pleasing to the newborn King.
So help us thou who didst become the child of man that we might become the children of God.
Amen.